(water trickling, dripping)
(dosimeter clicking)
(muffled labored breathing)
(flashlight whirring)
(whirring)
-(dosimeters clicking)
-(man grunting)
(muffled voices)
(water sloshing)
(muffled grunts)
(sighs)
Is it possible that the water
has already killed them?
Yes.
Then what?
If it doesn't work?
(distant helicopters whopping)
(dosimeters clicking loudly)
(flashlights whirring)
(muffled grunts)
(dosimeters clicking loudly)
(banging on door)
(panting, grunting)
(gasping)
(soldiers applauding)
(indistinct cheering)
Get them
in the truck.
Get the hoses in!
Start pumping!
Uh, I'm here
to see my husband,
Vasily Ignatenko.
He's a firefighter
from Chernobyl.
I have permission.
Chernobyl?
I'm sorry, no visitors.
Well, but Major Burov told me,
-he said--
-No exceptions.
Please. I've come all the way
from Kievskaya Oblast.
Excuse me.
Excuse me, excuse me.
Who are you?
What are you doing here?
-I have a pass.
-You can't be here.
It's not safe.
I am here to see
my husband.
Vasily Ignatenko.
He's a firefighter
from Chernobyl.
I know who Ignatenko is,
but you can't.
I have permission.
I-I've...
You can see him
for 30 minutes,
not a minute more.
And you cannot touch
him in any way.
Do you understand?
-Yeah.
-Room 15.
Thank you.
-You're not pregnant,
are you?
-No.
I won't have to give
that to you.
There they are.
No, wait, wait, wait.
I haven't finished yet.
No, he hasn't.
Yeah, that's good.
Yeah, better.
Look who the cat
dragged in.
What did I tell you?
-There's no hiding
from you, is there?
-(both laughing)
(groans)
Easy, easy. It's okay.
We're all okay.
Yeah, we're okay.
(distant wind howling)
(distant dosimeter clicking)
(helicopter whomping)
(indistinct voices)
(dosimeter clicking)
(clicking grows louder)
How, how, how did this happen?
Who gave them the idea?
-Are you suggesting I did?
-Someone did.
Someone decided
that the evacuation zone
should be 30 kilometers,
when we know, here,
Cesium-137
in the Gomel district.
-That's 200 kilometers away!
-It was decided.
-Based on what?
-I don't know!
Forgive me. Maybe I've just
spent too much time in my lab.
Or maybe I'm just stupid.
Is this really the way
it all works?
An uninformed,
arbitrary decision
that will cost who knows
how many lives
made by some apparatchik,
some career party man?
I'm a career party man.
You should watch your tone,
Comrade Legasov.
Pikalov:
Comrades...
We have visual confirmation
that the fire is nearly
extinguished.
There has also been
a reduction in iodine 131
and cesium-137 emissions.
Good. Yes?
Pikalov:
But the temperature
is rising.
And, uh...
There's a spike
in zirconium-95.
It's from the cladding
on the fuel rods.
Meaning what?
The meltdown has begun.
(helicopters whomping)
(water drops plunking)
(distant man moans)
(moaning continues)
Man:
Get it off me!
(man wailing)
Nurse:
Stop moving!
-Get off him!
You're hurting him!
-(Vasily wailing)
-You can't be in here.
-What's happening to him?
-Get out!
-(Vasily screaming)
You can't be in here!
-(door slams)
-(muffled screaming)
(papers rustle)
(phone rings)
-Yes?
-Man (over phone):
Comrade Shcherbina is
on the phone.
Put him through.
Well?
Shcherbina:
The fire's nearly out.
The bubbler tanks
are being drained.
We have successfully eliminated
the risk of a thermal explosion.
(sighs)
And?
The situation inside the core
is deteriorating
faster than anticipated.
The concrete pad will last
for six to eight weeks,
but after that,
Legasov estimates a 50% chance
that the fuel will
breach the pad
and melt down into
the groundwater itself.
(stammers)
And where does this
groundwater go?
The Pripyat River,
which feeds into the Dnieper.
The primary water supply for
approximately 50 million people,
not to mention crops
and livestock,
would be... unusable.
We're recommending we install
a heat exchanger under the pad
to lower to core temperature
and halt the meltdown.
And in order to do that,
I'm told that we will need...
all of the liquid nitrogen
in the Soviet Union.
Gorbachev:
Oh.
- All right.
-Yeah, and of course,
we'll also need--
Whatever you need,
you have it.
- That should be
clear by now.
-Yes.
- Anything else?
-No, no, no. Thank you.
Yes. I'd like to address
the 30-kilometer
exclusion zone.
Wait, what?
Professor Legasov,
is that you?
What exclusion zone?
Minor details,
General Secretary.
Um, Premier Ryzhkov
has determined that--
If he determined,
then he determined.
Look, Professor Legasov,
you    are there
for one reason only.
Do you understand?
To make this stop.
I don't want questions.
I want to know when
this will be over.
If you mean when will
Chernobyl be completely safe,
the half-life of plutonium-239
is 24,000 years.
So perhaps we should just say,
"Not within our lifetimes."
(line clicks)
I think you and I
should take a walk.
It's late. I'm tired.
We're taking a walk.
(dog panting)
Was it it you want?
An apology?
Not gonna sit back and...
-(dog whining)
-(Legasov sighs)
What will happen
to our boys?
Which boys?
The divers?
The divers, the firefighters,
the men in the control room.
What does the radiation
do to them precisely?
At the levels some
of them were exposed?
Ionizing radiation tears
the cellular structure apart.
The skin blisters,
turns red, then black.
This is followed
by a latency period.
The immediate
effects subside.
The patient appears
to be recovering.
Healthy, even.
But they aren't.
This usually only lasts
for a day or two.
Continue.
Then the cellular damage
begins to manifest.
The bone marrow dies,
the immune system fails,
the organs and soft tissue
begin to decompose.
The arteries and veins
spill open like sieves,
to the point where you can't
even administer morphine
for the pain,
which is... unimaginable.
And then three days
to three weeks, you are dead.
That is what will happen
to those boys.
And what about us?
Well, we've...
We've gotten a steady dose,
but not as much of it.
Not strong enough
to kill the cells,
but consistent enough
to damage our DNA.
So, in time... cancer.
Or aplastic anemia.
Either way, fatal.
Well...
in a sense, it would seem we've
gotten off easy then, Valery.
I've seen them before.
Now you know why
I wanted to take a walk.
We can presume
the work site is bugged.
And our rooms,
even our bathrooms.
They've been here
the whole time.
Of course they've been
here the whole time.
But if we're seeing them
out in the open now,
it's because
they want us to know.
(distant helicopters thrumming)
(door opens, closes)
Khomyuk:
You've seen that?
The fuel is melting
faster than we expected.
I know. I have a plan.
Heat exchanger, I hope.
Yes.
There's something I've wanted
to ask you, comrade,
but I see you're already asking
yourself the same question.
Why did it explode?
I've worked the numbers
over and over,
presuming the worst possible
conditions in an RBMK reactor.
And I always get
the same answer.
Which is?
It's not possible.
And yet...
You're not going
to solve this here.
Not on paper.
Everyone who was
in the control room,
Dyatlov, Akimov, Toptunov,
they're all in Moscow,
Hospital Number 6.
We need to find out exactly
what happened that night,
moment by moment,
decision by decision.
Go now while
they're still alive.
Talk to them.
Because if we don't find out
how this happened,
it will happen again.
And, Khomyuk...
be careful.
(elevator dings)
(trucks rumbling)
Well, fuck you!
(men laughing)
Hey, here's one, here's one.
What's as big as a house,
burns 20 liters
of fuel every hour,
puts out a shit-load
of smoke and noise,
and cuts an apple
into three pieces?
A Soviet machine made to cut
apples into four pieces!
(men laughing)
-Who's in charge here?
-Glukhov: I'm the crew chief.
I am Shadov,
minister of coal industries.
We know who you are.
How many men do you have?
On this shift, 45 here,
a hundred in total.
I need all 100 men
to gather their equipment
and get in the trucks.
Do you? To where?
That's classified.
Come on, then.
Start shooting.
You haven't got enough
bullets for all of us.
Kill as many as you can,
whoever's left,
they'll beat the living piss
out of each of you.
-Soldier: You can't talk
to us like that!
-Shut the fuck up!
This is Tula.
This is our mine.
We don't leave
unless we know why.
Mm.
You're going to Chernobyl.
Do you know
what's happened there?
We dig up coal, not bodies.
The reactor fuel is going
to sink into the ground
and poison the water
from Kiev to the Black Sea.
All of it.
Forever, they say.
They want you to stop
that from happening.
And how are
we supposed to do that?
They didn't tell me,
because I don't need to know.
Do you need to know,
or have you heard enough?
(pats)
(men muttering)
Now you look like
the minister of coal.
(labored breathing)
(moans softly)
Vasya?
(inhales sharply)
(softly):
No, no, no.
They told you no touching.
It's not safe.
They touch you.
(kisses)
If it's safe for them,
it's safe for me.
(breathing shakily)
Where are the others?
They took them
to a special room.
They won't tell me where.
Will you open the curtains?
-Hmm?
-Open the curtains.
Aah.
(panting)
(grunts softly)
(laughing)
Please, tell me
what you see outside.
Tell me everything.
Huh.
I can see the Red Square.
And...
the Kremlin.
Spasskaya Tower,
the Mausoleum.
You see St. Basil's?
Yeah.
Ah.
Yes, it's beautiful.
I told you.
I told you I'd show
you Moscow, remember?
-Huh?
-Yeah. Yes.
Thank you.
(softly panting)
(man groans)
(man retches)
(labored breathing)
I'm not eating that.
It's shit.
Get me something else.
I'm not a nurse,
Comrade Dyatlov.
I'm a nuclear physicist.
Well, then, Comrade
Nuclear Physicist...
unless you happen to have
a butter and caviar sandwich
on you,
you can get the fuck
out of my room.
What?
I'm not good at this, Boris.
The lying.
Have you ever spent
time with miners?
No.
My advice: tell the truth.
These men work in the dark.
They see everything.
Andrei Glukhov, crew chief.
Do these work?
To an extent.
Of course.
So what's the job?
We need to install a liquid
nitrogen heat exchanger
underneath this concrete pad.
There's no way to approach
from the interior
of the building,
so you have to get at it
from underground.
-And what's above the pad?
-The core of
the nuclear reactor,
which is melting down.
What? Like...
Essentially.
Is it gonna fall
on top of us?
Not if you're done
within six weeks.
Dimensions?
Break ground here,
dig a tunnel
150 meters to here,
excavate a space
30 by 30 meters
for the heat exchanger.
And because we need to keep
disruption of the ground above
to a minimum,
you can't use
any heavy machinery.
It has to be done by hand.
Then I need more men.
Four hundred at least.
We'll have to work
around the clock.
How deep do you want
this tunnel? Six meters?
-Twelve.
-Twelve? Why?
For your protection.
At that depth,
you'll be shielded from
much of the radiation.
The entrance to the tunnel
won't be 12 meters below ground.
No.
And we're not 12 meters
below ground now.
No. We're not.
Shcherbina:
We have some equipment
here on site.
More will arrive
by midnight.
You can start
in the morning.
No. We start now.
I don't want my men here
one more second than
they need to be.
If these worked,
you'd be wearing them.
(sighs)
Are they all like that?
They're all like that.
(lantern rattling)
(men grunting)
(men shouting indistinctly)
Miner:
Yes?
-What's it up to?
-Uh, 50 degrees.
Fuck!
Glukhov:
Hey!
Hey you!
-We need fans.
-For what purpose?
What do you mean,
"For what purpose?"
To dig your fucking tunnel,
that's why.
-Who's talking to you?
-Whoa, whoa. Comrades.
It's 50 degrees down there.
We can't breathe
without the masks,
we can't breathe
with the masks.
It's like a fucking oven.
We need ventilation.
Fans will put dust in the air,
the dust will go in your lungs.
I've been breathing dust
in my lungs for 20 years.
Not this dust.
I'm sorry.
For your own good,
no fans.
(man gasping quietly)
(labored breathing)
My name is Ulana Khomyuk.
I'm a nuclear physicist
with the Chernobyl Commission.
I want you to tell me
everything that happened
on the night of the accident.
Is that all right?
Yes.
I want to tell.
All right.
(wheezing)
Your official title was?
My name is Leonid
Fedorovych Toptunov.
I am the senior reactor
control chief engineer
at Chernobyl Nuclear
Power Plant.
Senior engineer?
How old are you?
(gasping):
I'm 25.
(gurney rattling)
Vasily (weakly):
Lyusya? Lyusya?
Yes, I'm here,
I'm here. I'm...
(labored breathing)
Have you been here
this whole time?
No one said
I should leave.
I did.
Thirty minutes, I said!
Well, where have you been?
When he's in pain?
When his sores
stick to his gown?
When he soils himself
five times a night?
I've been looking after him.
Where have you been?
I've been In the north
and west wing,
where there are dozens
of patients from Chernobyl
exactly like him.
-It isn't safe for you here.
-He's my husband.
Not anymore.
He's something else now.
Do you understand?
He's dangerous to you.
He's burned.
Go home.
Please.
It won't take much longer.
I, uh...
I don't want him
to die alone.
Stay on the other side
of the plastic.
Or I'll have you
removed by security.
-(door opens, closes)
-(labored breathing)
(Vasily wheezing)
-Lyusya?
-Yes, my love.
Is it day?
No, it's nighttime now.
I think I had a dream,
it's just gone.
Vasya.
We're going to have a baby.
(labored breathing)
(door opens, closes)
The fire's out.
It's out, Valera.
The miners are making
incredible progress.
They say the whole job
will be finished in four weeks.
Four weeks.
Can you believe that?
I know the job isn't over.
But it's the beginning
of the end.
-(knocking)
-(door opens)
I'm sorry to bother you,
Deputy Minister, but...
it is the miners.
-(metal striking dirt)
-(miners grunting, coughing)
(indistinct shouting)
What?
You wouldn't give us fans,
it's too hot for clothes.
So we're digging the old way.
This is how our fathers mined.
We're still wearing
the fucking hats.
What do you want?
You're not as protected now.
Are you telling me
it will make a difference?
When this is over,
will they be looked after?
I don't know.
You don't know.
(labored breathing)
So the power level jumped
from 200 to 400 megawatts?
Yes.
Very fast.
Why didn't you initiate
an emergency shutdown?
Why didn't you press
the AZ-5 button?
We did.
I reported the increase
to Akimov,
and he pressed
the button.
Leonid, that's...
that's not possible.
He did.
I s-swear.
I saw him do it.
And that's
when it exploded.
What?
(door opens)
(cart rattling)
Khomyuk:
Um...
-Which room is Akimov?
-Twenty-seven.
(crying)
Akimov:
I pressed it...
before the explosion.
Before.
(weakly):
But why?
Why would that happen?
I shut it down.
I pressed AZ-5.
(Khomyuk breathes shakily)
Thank you, Comrade Akimov.
(labored breathing)
Akimov:
I did everything right.
(Khomyuk sighs)
(whispering):
Get out.
Get out. Get out of here.
Let me go! Let me go!
Stop it! Stop it!
You let her in that room?
Inside the plastic,
touching him?
-Did you know she's pregnant?
-It's not true!
-What have you done?
-What kind of place is this?
Where is her protection?
-Do you have any idea
what you're dealing with?
-Of course I do.
-Please, I do not--
-No.
-People are going
to hear about this.
-Wait.
People are going to hear.
Do you understand?
Everyone is going to hear.
Man:
What is everyone
gonna hear?
I am with the official
Chernobyl Commission,
and I've been authorized
by Valery Legasov.
-You can check this.
My name is Ulana--
-We know who you are.
What is everyone gonna hear?
Shcherbina;
You have your notes?
Yes.
Khomyuk was arrested
last night.
What? Why?
I don't know.
-Was it--?
-Of course it was.
I'm working on it.
-Boris--
-I'm working on it.
What more do you
want from me?
Fix your tie.
(door opens)
They'll see you now.
After thousands of sorties,
our brave helicopter crews
successfully
extinguished the fire.
The miners are working
heroically to ensure
that the fuel does not
reach the groundwater.
And furthermore,
there is no longer
a threat of
additional explosion.
The Soviet people
have faced the challenge
and risen to the task,
and they and everyone
in this room are to be
commended.
Lastly, Professor Legasov
and I have been vigilant
to protect the security
interests of the State.
And since the unfortunate
release of information
directly following
the accident,
we believe that there
has been no further lapse.
Comrade Charkov,
we hope we have lived up
to the highest standards
of the KGB.
You have.
Shcherbina:
Thank you.
Professor Legasov
will now speak about
the work that remains.
Thank you.
Deputy Chairman Shcherbina
has given you the good news,
and it is good.
The immediate danger is over.
Now, I'm afraid,
a long war must begin.
There is an enormous amount
of radioactive debris
and contamination
spread out across a zone
of approximately
2600 square kilometers.
This entire region must be
completely evacuated.
We must go to every town,
every village to ensure this.
And all animals still
surviving within the zone,
whether domesticated or wild,
must be presumed contaminated
and will have to be destroyed
to prevent the spread
of radiation and disease.
In the immediate area
surrounding Chernobyl,
uh, every rock, every tree,
the very ground itself,
has absorbed a dangerous
amount of radionuclides,
which will be carried
by the wind and the rain
if left exposed.
So we will have to raze
entire forests.
We will have to rip up
the top layer of earth
and bury it under itself,
approximately,
100 square kilometers.
Um, and finally,
we will need to construct
a containment structure
around the power plant itself,
which will, of course,
still be extremely...
There will be deaths.
What amount of time,
and how many men
do you require?
We expect this liquidation
effort to take three years
and approximately 750,000 men,
including a number of doctors
and structural engineers.
How many deaths?
Thousands.
Perhaps tens of thousands.
Gorbachev:
Begin at once.
(men murmuring)
-Legasov: Comrade Charkov.
-Shcherbina: Valery!
Yes, Professor?
My associate was
arrested last night.
Oh?
I mean no disrespect,
but I was wondering
if you could tell me why.
I assure you, I don't know
who you're talking about.
She was arrested
by the KGB.
You are the first deputy
chairman of the KGB.
I am.
That's why I don't have
to bother with arresting
people anymore.
But you are bothering
with having us followed.
I think the deputy
chairman is busy.
No, no. It's perfectly
understandable.
Comrade, I know you've heard
the stories about us.
When I hear them,
even I am shocked.
But we are not
what people say.
Yes, people are
following you.
People are following
those people.
You see them?
They follow me.
The KGB is a circle
of accountability.
Nothing more.
You know the work
we're doing here.
-You really don't trust us?
-Of course I do.
But you know
the old Russian proverb:
"Trust but verify."
And the Americans think that
Ronald Reagan thought that up.
Can you imagine?
It was very nice
speaking with you.
I need her.
So you will be
accountable for her?
Then it's done.
-Her name is--
-I know who she is.
Good day, Professor.
No, that went
surprisingly well.
You came off like
a naive idiot.
And naive idiots
are not a threat.
Man:
I'll come back when
the paperwork is complete.
-Are you all right?
-They didn't hurt me.
They let a pregnant woman
into a room with a...
(sighs)
It doesn't matter.
They were stupid.
I was stupid.
Dyatlov won't talk to me.
Akimov, yes,
Toptunov, yes, but...
(sighs)
Valery,
Akimov...
his face was gone.
You want to stop?
Is that a choice I even have?
Do you think the fuel will
actually melt through
the concrete pad?
I don't know.
A 40% chance maybe.
I said 50.
(chuckles)
Either way, the numbers
mean the same thing:
"Maybe."
(sighing)
Maybe the core will melt
through to the groundwater.
Maybe the miners who I've told
to dig under the reactor
will save millions of lives.
Maybe I'm killing them
for nothing.
I don't want to do
this anymore.
I want to stop.
But I can't.
I don't think you have
a choice any more than I do.
I think,
despite the stupidity,
the lies, even this...
you are compelled.
The problem has been assigned,
and you will stop at nothing
until you find an answer.
Because that is
who you are.
A lunatic, then.
A scientist.
(door unlocking)
Did you know that they were
running a safety test?
-Yeah.
-There's something else.
Akimov says
they shut the reactor down,
and Toptunov confirms it.
-They pressed AZ-5.
-Apparently not soon enough.
No.
They say Akimov
pressed AZ-5,
and then
the reactor exploded.
If it had been just one of them,
I would have put it under
faulty memory
or delusion even,
but they both agreed.
They were adamant.
Comrade?
-Do you think it's possible?
-I think it makes no sense.
I think it's what
I would say if I was trying
to cover my own mistakes.
But?
I believed them.
Then you should pursue it.
We have to pursue
every possibility,
no matter how unlikely,
no matter what
or who's to blame.
I'll go back to the hospital
and reinterview Akimov
and Toptunov.
If they're still awake.
They're not.
Guard:
Khomyuk.
(soldier speaking indistinctly)
(speaks indistinctly)
(truck rumbling)
(dosimeter clicking)
♪ (FOLK MUSIC PLAYING) ♪
ULYANA KHOMYUK:
To hell with our lives.
Someone has to start
telling the truth.
ANATOLY DYATLOV:
You think the right question
will get you the truth?
I know they're listening.
There is no truth.
(WOMAN YELPS)
♪ (MUSIC CONCLUDES) ♪